The most widely used invasive treatment
to treat angina or coronary artery disease
are percutaneous coronary intervention.
P c I also called percutaneous transluminal
coronary angioplasty, P T C A, and.
Coronary artery bypass graft surgery
in C A B G.
The surgeon will bypass
the blockage using grafts.
One end of the graft is attached
to the aorta and the other to the
coronary artery beyond the blockage.
The surgery is done by many methods
in the traditional form of bypass surgery.
The surgeon makes a vertical
incision on the chest to expose it.
The breast bone is cut
using an electric sore.
The heart can be seen beating in the chest
during the surgery.
The heart is called and stopped so that
the surgeon can perform the surgery easily.
The oxygen requirement
of the heart decreases.
During this period.
The function of the heart and the lungs is
taken over by the heart lung bypass machine.
This machine is controlled by a technician.
The profusionist simultaneously,
depending upon the number of bypass
grafts needed, another surgeon will
dissect and remove the vein from the.
Arm or vorax.
This process is called harvesting.
The graft taken from the
leg is of the sphs vein.
The arterial grafts are from the forearm
called the radial or ulna artery.
The veins or arteries for grafting
can also be harvested, endoscopic.
Where a small incision is made to remove
the vein or artery for grafting, many
times an artery from the chest wall is also
used, called the internal memory artery.
One end of the graft is stitched to the
largest artery arising from the heart called
the aorta, and the other end is stitched
beyond the blockage on the coronary artery,
thus creating a new channel for the blood.
After the surgery is completed, the bypass
machine is slowly switched off and the heart
is restarted using drugs and electric shock.
The chest wall is then closed.
The patient is then shifted to the intensive
cardiac care unit for further management.
C A B G is also performed using advanced
techniques like minimally invasive surgery.
Here the surgery is done
through small incisions.
The surgery is suitable for patients
requiring one to two bypasses in the
arteries on the front of the heart.
In some of the cases, an advanced
technique called beating heart
or off pump surgery is performed.
It is performed using a stabilizing
device to restrict the movement of
small segments of the heart while the
patient's heart continues to beat.
This allows the surgeon to operate
without the use of the heart lung.
Used in conventional cardiac surgeries, some
changes in lifestyle helps manage angina.
It is important to exercise regularly,
have regular checkups with a
doctor for blood pressure and for
complications of hypertension, manage
stress levels effectively and take
prescribed medication regularly.